Chenhao Li | PhD

⊠ lichenhao.sg@gmail.com

Summary

An experienced computational biologist with strong passion for understanding biology through computational approaches. Proficient in mining, visualizing, interpreting and modelling high-throughput sequencing data. Interested in a broad range of biological problems, especially understanding the dynamics of microbial communities.

Education

PhD in Computer Science

National University of Singapore

Jan 2015-Apr 2019

Thesis: Modelling Approaches to Predicting Microbial Interactions

Supervisors: Niranjan Nagarajan, Limsoon Wong

- Award for outstanding achievement 2018 (GIS Graduate Student Prize)
- Award for excellence in teaching 2018 (Honor List of Student Tutors)

BSc (Hon.) in Computational Biology

National University of Singapore

Aug 2010-Jun 2014

Cumulative Average Point: 4.7/5.0 (First Class Honours)

- o Best academic exercise in Computational Biology 2014 (Lijen Industrial Development Medal)
- Best student in Computer Science stream 2011 (Lim Soo Peng Book Prize)
- o Dean's List (2011/2012 Semester II and 2013/2014 Semester I)
- Full scholarship for Chinese students awarded by the Ministry of Education 2009 (SM3)

Work Experience

Research Fellow

Xavier lab at Massachusetts General Hospital and Broad Institute

Dec 2020 - Present

- Analysis of single cell and spatial transcriptomics data of gut tissues
- Investigation of associations of gut microbiome and cardiovascular disease risks using multiomics data

Research Associate

Genome Institute of Singapore

Apr 2020 - Nov 2020

- o Build and maintain bioinformatics infrastructure for COVID-19 sample analysis
- Lead bioinformatics analysis of skin metagenomics samples

Postdoctoral Fellow

Genome Institute of Singapore

Apr 2019 - Mar 2020

- Investigate antibiotics resistant bacteria in environmental samples
- Build and maintain data handling system for nanopore sequencing data for the institute
- Predict ecological interactions between microbial species

Bioinformatics specialist

Genome Institute of Singapore

Jul 2014 - Mar 2019

- Mine association between disease and human microbiome
- Predict ecological interactions between microbial species
- o Design, optimise and maintain high-performance pipelines for sequencing data analysis
- Guide and train attachment students

Technical skills

Github page: https://github.com/lch14forever

- Programming languages: (advanced) R, Python and Linux bash scripting; (intermediate) Javascript, C, C++, MATLAB, JAVA, Perl, HTML, PHP and SCALA
- Bioinformatics: (advanced) workflow languages (Nextflow, Snakemake, Bpipe), next-generation sequencing data analysis (shotgun metagenomics, amplicon sequencing, RNA-Seq, whole genome sequencing, Single cell RNA-Seq and spatial transcriptomics)
- Scientific computing: high performance computing environments (cluster), cloud computing (AWS, GCP)
- Others: (advanced) git, docker

Software

- BEEM-static An R package for inferring microbial interactions based on Lotka-Volterra models from cross-sectional microbiome sequencing data. https://github.com/lch14forever/ BEEM-static
- 2. BEEM Estimating Lotka-Volterra models from time-course microbiome sequencing data. https://github.com/lch14forever/BEEM
- 3. shotgunmetagenomics-nf A reference-based pipeline for shotgun metagenomics. https://github.com/lch14forever/shotgunmetagenomics-nf
- 4. MicrobiomeViz An R package for visualising microbiome data. https://github.com/lch14forever/microbiomeViz

Publications (*: first author, #: correspondance author)

Under review

 H. Hu*, Y. Tan*, C. Li*, ..., L. Dai. StrainPanDA: linked reconstruction of strain composition and gene content profiles via pangenome-based decomposition of metagenomic data. BioRxiv. (2022).

Published

- 1. F. Meyer, A. Fritz, ..., C. Li, ..., A. C. McHardy. Critical Assessment of Metagenome Interpretation the second round of challenges. Nature Methods. (2022).
- 2. C. Li*#, T. V. Av-Shalom, J. W. G. Tan, J. S. Kwah, K. R. Chng, N. Nagarajan*. BEEM-Static: Accurate inference of ecological interactions from cross-sectional metagenomic data. PLOS Computational Biology. (2021).
- A global metagenomic map of urban microbiomes and antimicrobial resistance. Cell. (2021). (MetaSUB consortium).
- 4. J. G. A. Aw, S. W. Lim, J. X. Wang, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan, Y. Wan. Determination of isoform-specific RNA structure with nanopore long reads. Nature Biotechnology. (2021).
- 5. A. S. L. Tay*, **C. Li***, T. Nandi*, ..., N. Nagarajan, J. Common. Atopic dermatitis microbiomes stratifiy into ecological dermotypes enabling microbial virulence and disease severity. **The Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology**. (2021)
- 6. K. R. Chng, T. Ghosh, Y. H. Tan, T. Nandi, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Metagenome-wide association analysis identifies microbial determinants of post-antibiotic ecological recovery in the gut. Nature Ecology and Evolution. (2020).
- K. R. Chng*, C. Li*, D. Bertrand*, ..., N. Nagarajan. A cartography of opportunistic pathogens and antibiotic-resistance genes in a tertiary hospital environment. Nature Medicine. (2020).
- 8. C. Li*, K. R. Chng, T. V. Av-Shalom, ..., N. Nagarajan. An expectation-maximization algorithm enables accurate ecological modeling using longitudinal microbiome sequencing data. Microbiome. (2019).
- 9. D. Bertrand, J. Shaw, M. Narayan, A. H. Q. Ng, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Nanopore sequencing enables high-resolution analysis of resistance determinants and mobile elements in the human gut microbiome. Nature Biotechnology. (2019).
- D. Bertrand, S. Drissler, B. Chia, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. ConsensusDriver improves upon individual algorithms for predicting driver alterations in different cancer types and individual patients — A Toolbox For Precision Oncology. Cancer Research. (2018).
- 11. Y. O. Zhu, P. P. K. Aw, P. F. de Sessions, ..., C. Li, ..., M. Hibberd. Single-virion

- sequencing of lamivudine-treated HBV populations reveal population evolution dynamics and demographic history. **BMC Genomics**. (2017).
- 12. K. M. K. Lim, C. Li, K. R. Chng, N. Nagarajan. @MInter: Automated text-mining of microbial interactions. Bioinformatics. (2016).
- 13. K. R. Chng, S. H. Chan, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Tissue microbiome profiling identifies an enrichment of specific enteric bacteria in *Opisthorchis viverrini* associated cholangiocarcinoma. EBioMedicine. (2016).
- K. R. Chng, A. S. L. Tay, C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Whole metagenome profiling reveals skin microbiome dependent susceptibility to atopic dermatitis flares. Nature Microbiology. (2016).
- 15. **C.** Li*, K. R. Chng, K. M. K. Lim, N. Nagarajan. Predicting Microbial Interactions through Computational Approaches. **Methods**. (2016).
- 16. **C. Li***, K. R. Chng*, E. J. H. Boey, ..., N. Nagarajan. INC-Seq: Accurate single molecule reads using nanopore sequencing. **GigaScience**. (2016).
- G. Wu, H. Zhao, C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Genus-wide comparative genomics of Malassezia delineates its phylogeny, physiology, and niche adaptation on human skin. PLOS Genetics. (2015).
- 18. A. D. Ewing, et al. Combining tumor genome simulation with crowdsourcing to benchmark somatic single-nucleotide-variant detection. Nature Methods. (2015). (DREAM Challenge team Lofreq).

Teaching experience

Teaching assistant for CS1010X (Programming Methodology)

National University of Singapore

Jan 2018 - Jun 2018

Teaching assistant for LSM2241 (Introduction to Bioinformatics)

National University of Singapore

Aug 2013 - Dec 2013

Talks

 System Biology Modeling with Compositional Microbiome Data Reveals Personalized Gut Microbial Dynamics and Keystone Species. International Human Microbiome Congress 2018, Ireland.

Academic Service

 Ad hoc reviewer for Bioinformatics, GigaScience, Nature Methods, PeerJ, Scientific Reports, Microbiome, Journal of Genetics and Genomics